前情提要
没多少干净水能喝了 避难所居民
Ain't much stays clean up here, Vaultie.
你等着瞧吧
You'll see.
我觉得我们不应该帮助这些人 他们是杀人犯
I don't think it's our job to help these people.They're murderers.
你有什么建议？
So what do you propose we do?
我们可以用他们准备对待我们的方式
We can do what they would've done to us.
哇哦
Wow.
他们杀了我丈夫
They killed my husband.
如果你爸爸还在 他… 他会做该做的事
If your father were here, he'd...he'd do the right thing.
你还好吗？
You okay?
因为帮露西打开避难所大门
The whole "opening the vault door for Lucy" thing
和议会闹得不愉快
didn't sit too well with the council, so...
看来我以后不能再看大门了
I guess I'm not Gate-Keeper anymore.
我需要那颗脑袋 只有这样我才能把我爸爸救回来
I need the head.It's the only way I can get my father back.
你不能这样对待别人
You can't treat people like this!
是吗 为什么不能？
Yeah, why is that?
因为那条黄金法则
Because of the Golden Rule.
废土有废土的黄金法则
Wasteland's got its own golden rule.
胡说八道总会让人分心
Thou shalt get sidetracked by bullshit every goddamn time.
西区医疗诊所
罗杰！
Roger.
我叫罗杰
My name is Roger.
我叫罗杰！
罗杰
Roger.
罗杰 我叫罗杰
Roger. My name is Roger.
我叫罗杰
My name is Roger.
嗨 罗杰
Hey, Rog.
嗨
Hey. Hey.
没想到你会来这里
Fancy seeing you out here.
你也是为了得到那笔赏金 是吧？
You out for that bounty, too, huh?
是的
Yep.
可恶！
Oh, shit.
你感觉怎么样？
- How you feeling? - Oh...
你懂的 这里的日子很不好过
You know... it's hard out here.
那些该死的滑皮肤人类很残忍
Dang smoothies can be so unkind.
我看你也逮到了一个滑皮肤
I see you got a smoothie of your own.
你要变成狂尸鬼了？
You're turning.
也许吧
Yeah. Yeah, maybe.
也许
Maybe.
嘿 你应该不会碰巧随身带着药吧？
Hey, you-you don't happen to have any vials, do you?
只要吸一小口 我就能恢复健康了
Just one little puff and I'll be back on my feet.
你知道我以后会还你的
You know I'm good for it.
抱歉 罗杰 药都用完了
I'm sorry, Roger. I'm all out.
没关系
That's okay. That's okay.
不过 你和你的滑皮肤朋友…
Though, um, you and your smooth-faced friend, you, um...
你俩最好赶紧离开 不然场面会变得很难看
might want to clear out... before things get ugly.
之前我一直没事
I did okay.
28年来 我一直没变成狂尸鬼
Twenty-eight years since I first started showing.
该死！
Oh, hell.
不过没你坚持的时间长
Not as long as you, though.
你比我们所有人坚持的时间都长
You've outlasted us all.
你是从什么时候起 开始在废土生活的？
How long since you first started wastelanding?
很久很久以前
A long time.
你用了不少药啊
That's a lot of vials.
我一直都很能赚钱 罗杰
Well, I've always been good at making money, Roger.
说起来
Say...
还记得当初的食物有多美味吗？
...you remember how good food used to taste?
布拉科芝士通心粉
Yeah. BlamCo Mac & Cheese.
冰淇淋和苹果派
Ice cream and apple pie.
天啊！
Hot damn.
苹果派
Apple pie.
你知道吗 我妈妈过去常放…
You know, my mom used to...
你为什么要这么做？
Wait...Why'd you do that?
你真是个变态
He was sick.
住手！快点！我…
Stop. Stop, stop. Please, I...
我知道在这里生存很难 但是你也不该…
No, I know it's hard up here, but you don't... you don't have...
你不该诉诸于…
you don't have to resort to... to...
诉诸于…你刚才说你叫什么？
What'd you say your name was?
露西麦克莱恩
Lucy MacLean.
麦克莱恩
MacLean?
好吧 露西麦克莱恩
Well, Lucy MacLean,
亲爱的 废土可不是什么美食天堂
it ain't all canned peaches and marmalade left up here, sweetheart.
有时候 大家必须同类相食
Sometimes a fella's got to eat a fella.
我的避难所也有过艰难时期
You know, my vault has endured hardship, too.
77年时曾经闹过大瘟疫
In the Great Plague of '77,
那时候大家都被迫隔离 不能在农场里一起干活
everyone had to quarantine, they couldn't work the farms together.
很多人都忍饥挨饿
People starved.
包括我妈妈
My mother included.
我爸爸瘦到了58公斤
My dad dropped to 128 pounds,
但他依然拒绝同类相食
and he still refused to do anything like this.
怎么了？你在笑什么？
What? What's so funny?
有些人说自己没做过
Well, there's what people say they did
未必真的没做过
and what they really did.
当年你爸爸肯定第一个跑去吃人
I'll bet your daddy was first in line at the cookout.
我敢打赌 他有一个围嘴 上边画着他邻居的屁股
I bet he had a bib with a drawing of his neighbor's ass on there.
你怎么能过这样的生活？
How do you live like this?
为什么还要继续活下去呢？
Why keep going?
问得真好 那我也要问你一个问题
Well, one good question deserves another.
为什么所有的活都要由我来干？
Why the fuck am I doing all the work?
来吧 避难所居民
Now come on, Vaultie.
你不动手割 屁股肉干可没得吃
Ass jerky don't make itself.
辐射
请投雷吉迈克菲当监管人
与未来的监管人伍迪合作
-早上好 伍迪 -早上好 雷吉
- Morning, Woody. - Morning, Reg.
你的海报做得不错
- Nice work on your posters. - Oh, thanks, Reg.
谢谢 雷吉 我也一直在欣赏你的海报
I've been admiring yours as well.
问出什么了吗？
Any luck?
我问了他很多问题 他是谁 他的雇主是谁
I asked him all sorts of questions.Who he is, who he works for,
他的同伙为什么 要抓走麦克莱恩监管人
why his colleagues kidnapped Overseer MacLean.
他们组织的原则是什么 当然 他们未必有原则
What organizing principle, if any, they operate under.
他不开口？
Nothing, huh?
我们200年没交流过了
Two hundred years with no contact.
这家伙肯定经历了不少苦难
The terrible things this creature must have been through.
-他在做什么？ -糟糕
What's he doing? Oh, no.
先生 请停下来 你会受伤的
Sir? Please stop. You will injure yourself.
你去死吧！
Fuck you!
最好再给他打一针镇静剂
We better tranq him again.
是啊 这是为了他的安全着想 明天再来问吧
- For his own safety. - We'll try again tomorrow.
找到你了 我就知道你可能在这里
There you are.Thought you might be up here.
我做了派 你可以来一块
Made pie if you'd like a piece.
你第一次吃大黄派和冰淇淋时 我也在场
I was there the first time that you tried rhubarb pie and ice cream.
那天你真的吃了好多派
You sure did like pie that day.
我知道你想跟我谈谈 我在大会上说的那些话
You came here to talk to me about what I said at the assembly.
你为什么觉得我会谈那件事呢？
And why do you think that is?
因为那些话让人们很不安
It upset people.
你不喜欢看到人们不安
You don't like it when people get upset.
但你喜欢？
But you do?
不是只有你在想念你的父亲
You're not the only one that feels the absence of your father.
大家都很伤心 都很迷惘
People here are hurting.Disoriented.
如今你姐姐走了 麦克莱恩家只剩下你在这里了
And with your sister gone, you're the last standing MacLean.
你可能没意识到 你的话非常有分量
Your voice carries more weight than you might realize.
我藏起来了
I hid.
我们被突袭的时候 我藏进了储藏室里
During the raid, I got in a storage space and I hid.
这让你很生气吗？
Does that make you angry?
那很重要吗？
Why does it matter?
普通的男孩子…
Regular boys...
他们生气时 会在墙上撒尿
...can get angry and they'll just pee on the wall.
但像你这样聪明的男孩生气时…
When clever boys like you are angry...
这么说吧 你没看到 由此可能引发的后果 算你走运
You're lucky not to have seen where that can lead.
你要小心行事
Just tread lightly.
这是我对你唯一的要求
That's all I ask.
现在你能理解了吧
Now you're getting it.
经历了这些事 你还相信那条黄金法则吗？
How does that Golden Rule jibe with what's going through your head right now?
你究竟是什么？
What are you?
我就是你 亲爱的
Oh, I'm you, sweetie. You just give it a little time.
过段时间你就会有切身体会了
你以为能跑到哪儿去？你休想逃
Where you think you going? You ain't going nowhere.
终于现原形了 你这个小杀手
There you are, you little killer.
不要！
Aah!
认识了这么多天 这是咱俩有过的最好的“交流互动”
Now, that right there is the closest thing we've had to an honest exchange so far.
-嘿 -嘿
- Hey. - Hey.
我就是来看看你还好吗
I thought I'd just stop by and see how you're doing.
老实讲 不是很好
- Not great, to be honest. - Mm.
我先是失去了露西 接着又失去了守门人的工作
First I lost Lucy, and then I lost my job as the Gate-Keeper.
是啊 你是如何应对…
- Right. - How are you handling the, uh...
孩子还没出生就已痛失父亲的？
...death of the father of your unborn baby?
我也不太好
Same.
我刚才在收拾伯特的旧东西
I was actually just organizing some of Bert's things, and,
我想着或许有些可以送给你
well, I thought maybe you might want some of them?
好啊
Oh.
他只剩下这些东西了
This is all that's left of him.
他是个好人 斯蒂芬
He was a good man, Steph.
你真这么觉得？
You think so?
当然了 这还用问吗？
Of course. I mean, what can you say?
那个…
Well...
他非常爱护自己的鞋子
He took great care of his shoes.
这是他为数不多的爱好之一
You know, it was one of the few things he truly loved.
他一旦开始讲如何保养鞋子
Get him talking about shoe maintenance,
就会没完没了 直到大家都离开房间
and...he'd just carry on until everyone left the room.
我真的很爱他
I loved him so much.
但那些混蛋把他杀了
And those monsters took him away from me.
太可怕了 我恨那些家伙
Awful.Hate those guys.
如果你能收下伯特的鞋子 对我来说意义重大
It would mean a lot to me if you took Bert's shoes.
哇
Wow.
谢谢 斯蒂芬 我…
Thank you, Steph. I'll...
我会尽量多穿的
- I'll try to wear them. - Oh, good.
太好了 还有这个
And this...
伯特
Oh, Bert.
Bert... Bert.
伯特
- Okay... - Oh, Bert.
Oh, Bert.
伯特
Bert.
别脱下来 你能穿着做吗？
Oh, no, no, no.Could you just keep it on while we...?
-当然可以 抱歉 -没事
Oh, yeah, of course, I'm sorry.
我刚才可真傻
What was I thinking?
伯特
Oh, Bert.
-是的 我是伯特 -是啊
- Yes, I am Bert. - Yeah.
你湿得可真厉害
Now, that is one wet lady.
伯特
顶呱呱超市
交易
Transaction.
什么？
Yes?
我要两个月份量的药剂
Two-month supply of vials.
用一个状态完好的女性进行交换
Exchange one female. Mint condition.
几近完好
Near mint condition.
状态评分需要进行身体检查
Condition grading requires physical evaluation.
请把她送进来
Please send her in.
里面有什么？
What's in there?
你马上就知道了
You're about to find out.
你要卖了我？
You're selling me?
亲爱的 你在外边我也一样会毙了你
You got problems out here, too, sweetheart.
劝你还是进去吧 说不定会交好运
Best you try your luck behind that door.
快去
Go on.
-欢迎！ -什么鬼？
Welcome.
鬼？这里没有鬼
- What the fudge? - Fudge? There's no fudge here.
只有通用原子国际四号机
Only a General Atomics International Mark 4.
也就是在下 而你看起来是一位女性
That's what I am. You seem to be a woman.
拜托 先生 我叫露西麦克莱恩 我爸爸被带走了 我…
Please, sir, my name is Lucy MacLean.
我被绑架了
My dad's been taken and I-I-I've been kidnapped.
他就在外边…
He's right outside...
你断了一根手指头
I say, you've lost a finger.
那可不行
Ah, that won't do at all.
我们给你处理一下吧 跟我来
Let's get you taken care of. Follow me.
好吧
Okay.
抱歉 这里很乱 总觉得最近时光飞逝
Apologies for the mess.Time flies by lately.
自从我的时间感在大战中失灵后 这种感觉尤为明显
Especially since my temporal sensors went out in the Great War.
那应该至少是一周前的事情了
That must have been a week ago, at least.
你能坐在面前的轮床上吗？
Would you mind taking a seat on that gurney in front of you?
让我瞧瞧这里都有什么
Now, what have we here?
太胖了 已经萎缩了 这个正好
Too fat, too withered.Ah, this one'll do it.
好在不需要使用大拇指
Eh, you're lucky I don't have to use a thumb.
我们的手指储备库真是太差了
Our finger inventory's in a sorry state.
现在 请把手伸出来
Now, if you give me your hand...
好了 可能会有一点挤压感
Okay, you're going to feel a slight pinch.
-谢谢 我… -天啊
Thank you.
我很感谢你愿意帮我
- I say. - I really do appreciate this.
但听我说 有条大鱼吃了我的头 我需要找回那个头
But listen, a big fish ate my head, and I need my head to get back to my dad...
-这样才能找回我爸… -好了
There now.
看着好多了 是不是？
That's much better, isn't it?
-谢谢 我… -不用谢
- Thank you, that... - Not a problem.
感觉真的很不错
That feels really, really nice.
你想要穿什么材质的衣服？ 优质合成纤维？
Now, would you prefer a dressing of high-quality synthetic fibers,
经典棉质？还是舒适合成棉混纺？
classic cotton, or a comforting synthetic-cotton blend?
你这里有…真棉花吗？
You have... real cotton?
当然有 你没有吗？
Of course. Don't you?
谢谢
Thank you.
你知道吗… 那个把我带来这里的怪物 他…
You know, that... that creature that brought me here, he...
你看起来不高兴
You seem unhappy.
-他对我十分粗鲁 -真的吗？
- He did not treat me very courteously. - Really?
我告诉他 他没有遵守黄金法则
When I pointed out that he wasn't following the Golden Rule,
结果他往我脖子上套皮带 逼我喝水坑里的水
he put a leash around my neck and he made me drink from puddle water
我敢肯定 那其实是某种动物的尿
that I'm pretty sure was just some kind of animal pee.
听起来真有趣
Well, that is interesting.
我以为他送我来这里是要让我当性奴
- And I thought I was here to be a sex slave. - What?!
什么？不是 这想法也太恶心了！
No! What a disgusting idea.
我只是想要摘取你的器官
I'm simply going to harvest your organs.
甜点托盘来了
Dessert tray incoming.
嘿
Hey, hey.
你會從她那裡拿走那個
You gonna take that from her?
你會拿走那個？
You gonna take that?
嘿 诺曼
Hey, Norm.
维罗妮卡
Veronica.
等等 要给他们吃果冻蛋糕？
Wait, they're getting Jell-O cake?
我接到的命令是这样
Those are my orders.
不知道换做你爸 他会说什么
I wonder what your dad would say about this.
他会亲自给他们送蛋糕
He'd be handing them the cake himself.
是啊 他是个圣人
Yeah. He was a saint.
你想吃吗？
Do you want it?
没人会知道的
Nobody's gonna know.
好 我去把这个放进我的冰箱里
Yeah.I'm gonna put this in my fridge.
你看什么看？
What are you looking at?
关在笼子里的杀人犯
A murderer in a cage
你对我们犯下恶行
paying the price for what you did to us.
伤害了32号避难所的无辜群众 你必须要付出代价
For what you did to the innocent people in Vault 32.
我不知道 32号避难所当时在谋划什么
I don't know what the people in Vault 32 were up to.
但我知道那些人肯定不无辜
But it was anything but innocent.
33号避难所通讯日志
31、32、33…
31 and 32.
访问32号避难所记录…
拒绝访问
诺曼 嗨
Norm. Hi.
-想出去走走吗？ -好啊
Feel like getting out of the house?Yes.
前往32
Maybe he was messing with me,
那个掠夺者可能是在耍我 但他跟我说
but one of the raiders told me there was something up in 32.
32号避难所可能在搞什么阴谋
Uh-huh.
我实在不觉得这件事有趣 诺曼
Well, this isn't exactly fun for me, Norm.
-那你为什么要来？ -老实讲 我也不知道
Then why'd you come?To be honest, I don't know.
该不会是因为你还爱着我姐姐
You don't think it's because you're still in love with my sister
待在我身边会让你想起她吧？
and being around me reminds you of her?
-真不该这么做 -快来
This is so wrong.Come on.
你得看看这个
You have to see this.
真的不该这么做
Wrong, wrong, wrong.
明白了吗？
You see?
不管这里发生过什么事 那都是很久以前的事了
Whatever happened here happened a long time ago.
管理
最后一次检测到生物信号是在两年前
The last bio-signal detected was two years ago.
你们好啊
这只老鼠或许能给我们答案
这个啮齿动物聚集地 被叫做老鼠乌托邦
This rodent colony is called a mouse utopia.
这些老鼠在这里享受着美好的一切
Inside, the mice enjoy all the amenities...
它们能吃到各种美食 还能在垫子上睡觉
all the food they can eat, all the padding they can sleep on...
但最终会出现人口过剩问题
but eventually overpopulation occurs.
老鼠们争斗不休 只为抢夺不再丰富的食物
The mice fight for the once bountiful food, the once endless space.
不再广阔的空间 为了生存 它们不得不同类相食
They eat each other in their desperation to survive.
如果掠夺者来这里的时候 他们已经死了
So, if they were already dead when the raiders got here,
那杀死他们的凶手是谁？
who killed them?
看起来他们亲手掐死了对方
I mean, it looks like they strangled each other with their hands.
这太荒谬了 我们知道真相
It just doesn't make any sense.
我们自己的工厂制造的 新鲜牛奶冰淇淋！
露西
Lucy.
露西 亲爱的 你在这儿做什么？
Lucy, sweetie,what are you doing out here?
玛莎 我叫玛莎
My name is Martha.
Martha. My name is Martha.
玛莎 我叫玛莎
Martha. My name is Martha. Martha.
My name is Martha.
玛莎 我叫玛莎
Martha.
不好意思 打扰了 新人已经到了
Pardon the interruption.Our latest arrival has arrived.
天啊
Oh, shit.
对方要多少货 咔嚓？
What are they asking, Snip Snip?
60瓶
Sixty vials.
-没问题 -太好了
We can do 60.
快点摘除她的器官吧 这样等买家来了 就能有货了
- Fantastic. - Oh, do her now so she's ready for the next pickup.
先生 您一如既往地聪明
Excellent idea as always, sir.
-谢谢 咔嚓 -失陪了
Thanks, Snip Snip.Do excuse me.
这机器人真不错
Nice robot.
你是从哪里来的来着？
Where are you from again?
我从没去过那儿 希望有一天能去
Never been there myself. Hope to go there someday soon.
到了 我们开始吧 好吗？
Here we are. Let's get on with it, shall we?
不能让你的朋友等太久
We don't want to keep your associate waiting.
先生 你不能这样做
Sir, you can't do this.
求你了 我需要我的器官
Please, I need my organs.
别害怕 咔嚓咔嚓来几下 一切就结束了
Now, don't be afraid.A little snip-snip and it will all be over.
不要动
Hold still now.
一点都不疼
This won't hurt a bit.
不好意思
Excuse me.
你…我的…不好意思 女士 有没有什么…
没问题 什么都行 我很高兴 什么…
你好 什么都行 这里没有鬼
There's no fudge here.
艾巴索下水道清洁剂
我随时准备好服务
I am ever-ready to serve...
服务
to serve... to serve.
举起手来！
Hands up.
老实听我的话 我就不会伤害咔嚓
Do as I say, and Snip Snip doesn't get hurt.
呼叫所有汽車。
Calling all cars.
那货是个机器人好吗
It's a fucking robot.
是啊 你干脆拿空调当人质得了
Yeah, you might as well be holding an air conditioner hostage.
其实 拿空调当人质会让我有所触动
Well, an air conditioner sounds nice, though.
是啊 空调非常重要 但你懂我是什么意思
Yeah, an air conditioner would be a big deal.But you know what I mean.
当然懂
Totally. The question was,
问题是她懂你是什么意思吗？
does she know what you mean?
是的 我想我懂
Yeah. I think I do.
所以我才在他的注射管里 放了艾巴索清洁剂
That's why I put Abraxo Draining Fluid in his syringes.
咔嚓 告诉他们 艾巴索对人体有什么害处
Snip Snip, tell them what Abraxo does to the human body.
如果你的下水道被脏东西堵住了
If you've got a c-c-clog that's full of muck,
艾巴索清洁剂帮你轻松疏通
trust Abraxo Draining Fluid t-t-to get it unstuck.
本产品毒性非常大
It's v-v-very poisonous.
好吧 你可以离开这里
Okay, you can walk out of here.
不仅要放了我
Not just me.
还要放了他们
Them, too.
嘿 谢谢！
Hey, thank you.
我说的是 所有人
I said all of them.
女士 你不明白其他几个是什么
Lady, those-those ones, you don't understand...
不要害怕
Don't be scared.
你们自由了 走吧
You're free. Go.
狂尸鬼
天啊
Oh, gosh.
怎么了…你好啊
Hello there.
再见
Goodbye.
玛莎 我叫玛莎
Martha. My name is Martha.
没错 你叫玛莎
That's right. Your name is Martha.
不要
No. No.
玛莎 我叫玛莎
Martha. My name is Martha.
求你了
Please, please.
求你了 我知道你还留有人性 跟我聊聊
Come on, I know there's someone in there. Talk to me.
求你了！
Please!
不好意思 女士
Pardon me, madam.
我能帮你把今天过得更好吗？
Could I help you have a better day?
不需要 谢谢
No, thank you.
天啊
Oh, geez.
好吧
Okay.
看来很有可能他们是发疯了
I think it's safe to say they went bananas.
但这还是没法解释 掠夺者是怎么进来的
This still doesn't explain how the raiders got in.
管理层去死
These people were crazy.
这些人都疯了 如果当时有人幸存
If there were any survivors down here,
他们可能打开了大门 邀请掠夺者进来
they probably opened the door and welcomed the raiders right in.
避难所大门日志
正在访问日志…
上边显示门是从外边打开的
It says it was opened from the outside.
不 他们要有哔哔小子才能打开门
No.They'd need a Pip-Boy to open the door.
-他们确实有一个 -谁的？
They had one.Whose?
我妈妈的 罗丝麦克莱恩
My mom's.
不吃这些药 你就会变得像那些怪物一样吗？
You don't get these, you turn into one of those?
是这样吗？
That how it works?
也许最终我会变成你的同类
I may end up looking like you...
但我永远不会堕落成你这样
...but I'll never be like you.
这就是黄金法则 混蛋
Golden Rule, motherfucker.
好家伙
Are you shitting me?
我很愿意分享一部分给你们
Ah. I'd love to share some of this with y'all, but...
但可惜你们没被邀请
...y'all weren't invited to this party.
《来自死马镇的男人》 加州新月电影公司
放射王
有句墨西哥悼词是这么说的 “Feo, fuerte, y formal”
There's an old Mexican eulogy, "Feo, fuerte y formal."
意思是“此人丑陋 坚强且有尊严”
Means he was ugly, strong,and had dignity.
乔伊啊
Well, Joey...
我觉得你满足其中两点
...I'll give you two out of three on that front.
希望你喜欢子弹的味道 你这个混蛋共产分子
I hope you like the taste of lead, you commie son of a bitch.
呀！
Yee-haw!